<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: compiz | Mostly Unixish]]></title>
  <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/categories/compiz/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-12T08:54:36+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alan Franzoni]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unfreezing your desktop: when Compiz goes wrong]]></title>
    <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/2014/12/12/unfreeze-window-manager/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-12T08:50:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/2014/12/12/unfreeze-window-manager</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A desktop freeze is something that&rsquo;s not so rare nowadays &ndash; that&rsquo;s not good, but we shouldn&rsquo;t get desperate about that.</p>

<p>I like <a href="www.compiz.org">Compiz</a> with <a href="https://unity.ubuntu.com/">Unity Desktop</a> on my <a href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/TrustyTahr/ReleaseNotes">Ubuntu Trusty</a> very much; <strong>I feel it&rsquo;s a step forward compared to traditional desktops</strong>. The only major nuisance I had on the previous versions was the inability to disable the global menu (which I like by itself, but I don&rsquo;t like the global menu disappearing when the mouse is not over it), but you can now disable it and have the menu on the window &ndash; even though you can&rsquo;t still enable an always-visible behaviour.</p>

<p>The problem is: compiz sometimes gets buggy. Running a different window manager, like <a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/Metacity">metacity</a> and/or <a href="http://cgit.freedesktop.org/xorg/app/xcompmgr/">xcompmgr</a> just doesn&rsquo;t seem good, you can experience other issues and you&rsquo;re using the stack in a way it wasn&rsquo;t designed for. I don&rsquo;t like that approach.</p>

<p>So, what can you do when your desktop freezes? The symptoms are usually very clear: you can move your mouse, but you can&rsquo;t click nor type anything.</p>

<p><strong>You don&rsquo;t need to reboot nor to restart X.</strong> You can fix this without losing your work.</p>

<h2>Get a raw tty</h2>

<p>Press <em>Ctrl+Alt+F1</em> and get to a raw linux console, and access with your credentials.</p>

<h2>Find and kill your stuck process</h2>

<p><code>
pgrep compiz
</code></p>

<p>This will print the PID of our stuck window manager.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s kill it</p>

<p><code>
kill compiz
</code></p>

<p>This <strong>won&rsquo;t usually be enough</strong> because the process is really stuck: if you repeat the <em>pgrep</em> command above, you&rsquo;ll find it still running &ndash; i.e. pgrep will return the very same PID as above.</p>

<p>So let&rsquo;s kill it, really this time!</p>

<p><code>
kill -9 compiz
</code></p>

<p>Wait some 15-20 seconds.</p>

<p>Now, if you repeat the <code>pgrep</code> , you&rsquo;ll either see a) no result or b) a different PID.</p>

<p>If you see a different PID, it&rsquo;s Ubuntu that noticed the crashed process and relaunched it; press <em>Ctrl+Alt+F7</em>, and you should just get back a working desktop!</p>

<h2>Relaunching</h2>

<p>If you see nothing with pgrep, you&rsquo;ll need to relaunch Compiz manually.</p>

<p>You cannot simply relaunch compiz on the console, because it must connect to X: the proper way to do it is:</p>

<p><code>
DISPLAY=:0 compiz
</code></p>

<p>Now switch back to your X instance with <em>Ctrl+Alt+F7</em> and enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
