<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: security | Mostly Unixish]]></title>
  <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/categories/security/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-27T09:15:24+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alan Franzoni]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't give a shell to system users - use su]]></title>
    <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/2014/12/11/su-with-chosen-shell/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-11T13:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/2014/12/11/su-with-chosen-shell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I seem very ancientwisdom-oriented these days.</p>

<p>Sometimes you&rsquo;ve got a system user on your linux server that&rsquo;s used to run a specific service; it&rsquo;s a good practice to employ those users to achieve <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privilege_separation">privilege separation</a>, since it limits the impact of many security breaches. It&rsquo;s security 101, really.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve got a system user, most probably its shell would be <code>/bin/false</code> or <code>/bin/nologin</code>. Again, this is a good practice, since it would be harder for an attacker to gain shell access to your machine through that user.</p>

<p>But I find that many people just <strong>change</strong> such shell, because sometimes they need to customize the environment for a user, and if you try doing something like</p>

<p><code>
su - systemuser
</code></p>

<p>you&rsquo;ll find yourself just back to your original shell, because <strong>su</strong> tries to invoke the shell which is set for the target user, and <code>sudo</code> doesn&rsquo;t generally help here, because its <code>--shell</code> option doesn&rsquo;t start a proper login shell for that user (most of the environment is that of the calling user).</p>

<p>Very well, gentlemen: <strong>this is a wrongdoing and a potential security hole</strong>. You should <strong>never</strong> enable a shell for your system users. Instead, you should leverage an option of <strong>su</strong>:</p>

<p><code>
su - systemuser --shell /bin/bash
</code></p>

<p>That lets you choose your favourite shell on a per-launch basis.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
