<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sudo | Mostly Unixish]]></title>
  <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/categories/sudo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-11T14:27:12+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alan Franzoni]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I wish sudo would ask for my password less often]]></title>
    <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/2014/11/11/how-often-sudo-asks-for-your-password/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-11T13:28:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/2014/11/11/how-often-sudo-asks-for-your-password</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a <strong>very</strong> old trick, but I find many people doesn&rsquo;t know about it yet.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re using sudo <a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/RootSudo">(and you definitely should)</a>, one minor complaint is that you need to re-enter your password quite often.</p>

<p>One common pseudo-solution is to completely disable the password for executing sudo with such user; while it may be a good idea sometimes, it does decrease the overall security &ndash; if you happen to forget an open shell or screen/tmux lingering somewhere, you give total power to whoever gets in touch with it.</p>

<p>If you happen to let people into your sudo-enabled account with your ssh key, anybody that can get hold of your ssh key will get <strong>root access</strong> to your servers. It&rsquo;s not the best possible scenario.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a very simply workaround: just edit your sudoers file!</p>

<p><code>
sudo visudo
</code></p>

<p>and add a line like that (or modify it if it&rsquo;s already there)</p>

<p><code>
Defaults    timestamp_timeout=120
</code></p>

<p>This means that sudo will ask for a password every two hours instead of the default (15 minutes on most installations). You can use -1 in order to never let it expire (I don&rsquo;t suggest that &ndash; 8-10 hours should be enough for everybody.)</p>

<p>The only drawback is that such timeout is per shell, not system-wide &ndash; i.e. if you open multiple terminals, you&rsquo;ll have to enter the password again for each new terminal instance.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
