<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: dropbox | Mostly Unixish]]></title>
  <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/categories/dropbox/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-06T14:47:01+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alan Franzoni]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dropbox and Mercurial: and lived happily ever after]]></title>
    <link href="http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/2012/06/21/dropbox-and-mercurial-and-lived-happily-ever-after/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-21T13:12:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mostlyunixish.franzoni.eu/blog/2012/06/21/dropbox-and-mercurial-and-lived-happily-ever-after</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some days ago I ranted about an issue I had with Mercurial and Dropbox; basically, I did put a mercurial repo in a dropbox
folder, and ended up with <a href="http://twitter.com/franzeur/statuses/214769401055035392/">this kind of mess</a></p>

<p>Mercurial repos inside Dropbox are not a great idea after all. But I had one problem: I sometimes forget to push changes to some files, and Dropbox comes to the rescue; at the same time I need history for such files, and I don't want problems to arise.</p>

<p>I found quite an easy solution:</p>

<ul>
<li>Create your dropbox-aware folder, e.g. "somefolder"</li>
<li>create a .hg folder inside it, e.g. "somefolder/.hg"</li>
<li>now use your dropbox client, be it the CLI or the GUI, enable <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/help/175/en">Selective Sync</a> and remove such .hg folder from being synced on your current machine. You must take this step on all machines that you want to use with such technique.</li>
<li>disabling sync for .hg should remove it from the somefolder directory.</li>
</ul>


<p>Now you can use <code>hg init</code> inside "somefolder", and you'll obtain a non-synced hg repository.</p>

<p>What for? Whatever! I just create a repo on bitbucket and push/pull changes to/from here.</p>

<p>On other machines, after making sure you've excluded .hg from syncing, you can just use</p>

<p><code>hg clone -U YOUR_REPO_URL</code></p>

<p>to obtain such .hg directory.</p>

<p>This way:</p>

<ul>
<li>it's impossible to get errors or conflicts like the one I previously mentioned</li>
<li>you get full storicization</li>
<li>Dropbox syncs the actual working copy, letting you have the latest version always 100% synced without manual intervention.</li>
</ul>


<p>Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
